Let's talk about how Django interacts with databases.
Let's control the out of this for just a moment and open up this folder in VS Code
either with code.org by going to VS Code and saying file open and then opening this folder.
And let's open a Python file by using the QuickFind Control P or Command P and opening models.py.
And this will start the Python extension.
Make sure you click down here and ensure that the right virtual environment is selected for
me, it's dot m slash bin slash Python. And that will clear up any if you saw some squiggly
is before under here. That's because Django was not installed in the virtual environment
that VS Code selected. I'm not sure why it's not selecting the right thing at the moment
or recognizing my virtual environments. Maybe it's a weird setting on my side because it is
something that usually works quite well. So I've opened up models.py and models.py
lives in the blog folder but I recommend that you open that up via the QuickFind.
So this is a custom model that I've defined in Django. And it's got a few fields in it.
It's got a title which is a character field with a max link of 300. It's got a body which is a
text field. It's got a slug which is a newspaper term but you might see used commonly in blogs
blogs. So a slug is a way of taking a title and then adding removing any special characters, adding
dashes or underscores. So that some of that title can be in the URL for the blog post for SEO
and then we also have a created at field which is a date time field and a string representation
of our model. Now this model maps to a database, a SQLite database that we have on our systems
and we don't need to know anything about SQL or databases in order to use databases with Django
which is just great. Once we create our application here at the blog app, we're going to want to
make sure that when we open settings.py which is the global settings for our Django application
and we scroll down to installed apps. We want to make sure that we have a blog.apps.blog
config in here that tells Django to register various applications. Now the practical blog directory
is the project level directory where all the project specific settings live for this project.
The blog directory has app specific stuff in it for my blog. When you're working on small Django
projects, having multiple apps doesn't matter but let's say you are a company and practical blog
is your project. Now you might have an app for a blog. You might have an app for an e-commerce site.
You might have an app for a forum and those are all going to have their own individual folders in
Django where you can define your models and views and routes and everything for that specific app
in its own happy little namespace. Now I'm not going to talk about how to make my
migrations but if you do want to complete the final exercise, I recommend that you go back to
the section. Anytime you change your models, let's say you delete one of these or you add a new one,
you need to tell Django to make instructions for the database to match the new model and then
run those instructions. So let's say if you delete a field here, Django needs to issue instructions
to drop a column from a table in a database. In order to do that, you need to run a command called
make migrations. You can optionally pass in the name of the app here. It's called blog and then you
can run the migrate command and that will go ahead and update your database so that it matches
your latest models. If you want to work with models, you can do that in the Python shell.
I'm going to open up my terminal here and type in Python managed.py followed by the word shell.
This is going to bring up a special Django shell that knows a lot about how our project is structured.
So it's a little bit different than just a standard rep old. Now we can work with our models
and objects that we defined in Django in this shell. For example, I can say from blog.models
import post and that is the model that I had defined up there. Now I can query that model by saying,
sorry, post.objects.all is going to query all of the tables, all the rows in this table.
Currently, we don't have any. If I wanted to, I have an example for creating posts from the command
here. So let me just copy and paste this first post here. I'm defining all of the fields,
providing values for all of the fields. I defined up here, title, body, and slug. Everything
except for created at because I'm using this auto add auto now add equals true. That means when I
create a row in this database, it's going to automatically add the created at timestamp.
In order for me to save this into my database, I need to run first post.safe. And now,
when I rerun my query, my first post is in here.
Let's go ahead and open a new tab in VS code and start our server again. So Python managed
up UI run server. If you never exited your server in the first place and you try to run it again,
you might get an error about the port being busy or occupied. Know that means that you're
probably already running your server in a different tab. So there is my first post reflected
in the web page. We can interact with these models just like objects in Python.
There's a get method. So I can pass in to get get me where the slug is equal to first post.
And that will return the record I just created. If I say first post two, I'm going to get an
exception here. Post does not exist. If there's no post matching your query, it should make sense.
I can also use the .filter method. So get will get you one results.filter will get you a list.
And you'll see that you got a query set back. So if you have multiple items that match that query,
they'll come back there. This query set kind of acts like a list and you can treat it as one,
so you can call. Let's save this to a variable called results. You can call length on results.
You can get the first item in results. And just like a list, this will throw an exception
because we only have one item. This there is list index at a range. So the Django or it features a lot
of optimizations under the hood. And the best part is you really don't need to know about the
internal workings of databases to take full advantage of them.